John L. Spivak Papers
John L. Spivak Papers
1922-1973
Spivak, John Louis, 1897-
24 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, journalist, novelist. Correspondence (1930-1972); typescript drafts and revisions of books; galley proofs; and published articles and books.
148684
Biographical History
John L. Spivak (1897-1981), an investigative reporter and author whom fellow muckraker Lincoln Steffens described as "the best of us," was most concerned with the problems of the working class and the spread of fascism and anti-Semitism in Europe and the United States from the 1920s through the 1940s.
As a boy Spivak worked for a variety of factories in his hometown of New Haven, Connecticut, then landed a job as a cub reporter for the New Haven Union. Moving to New York, he worked at the Morning Sun, Evening Graphic, and the Call, the paper of the American Socialist Party. His first major break came when he traveled to West Virginia to cover the coal strikes that broke out after World War I. He then served briefly as a reporter and bureau chief in Berlin and Moscow for the International News Service and upon his return to the U.S. became a feature writer for leftist newspapers and magazines such as the New York Daily Worker, Ken, and the New Masses.
Spivak traveled throughout the South in the early 1930s interviewing prison camp officials and photographing camp atrocities and their corresponding punishment records. His novel, Georgia Nigger, depicting the brutality of prison camp chain gangs was serialized in the Daily Worker. His 1935 exposé in the New Masses charged a congressional committee with deliberately suppressing evidence of an offer made to Maj. Gen. Smedley D. Butler by Wall Street financiers to lead a military coup against the U.S. government and replace it with a fascist regime. He also investigated the anti-Semitic and financial activities of Charles E. Coughlin, the Catholic radio priest who founded the Shrine of the Little Flower in Royal Oak, Michigan. Most of Spivak's work, however, was dedicated to exposing fascism and underground Nazi spy groups in Central America, Europe, and the U.S. He wrote several "muckraking" books about these activities.
With the rise of McCarthyism, Spivak spent most of the 1950s and 1960s writing under several pen names for men's adventure and lifestyle magazines including Cavalier, Esquire, Fury, Male, and Man to Man. Intent on writing his autobiography, he and his wife, Mabel, retired to their farm in Easton, Pennsylvania. Not long afterwards he decided to come out of retirement to edit a consumer affairs column for the Easton newspaper where his work culminated in a federal investigation into the high-pressure sales tactics used by magazine circulation companies that resulted in new consumer protection laws. Spivak died in 1981, six months after his wife passed away. They had been married for 64 years and were survived by a daughter and grandson.
Spivak's writings include: Medical Trust Unmasked (L.S. Siegfried, 1929), Devil's Brigade (Brewer and Warren, Inc., 1930), Georgia Nigger (London, Wishart & Company, 1933), Plotting America's Pogroms: A Documented Exposéof Organized Anti-Semitism in the United States (The New Masses, 1934), America Faces the Barricades (Covici Friede Inc., 1935), Europe Under the Terror (Simon & Schuster, 1936), Secret Armies: the New Technique of Nazi Warfare (Modern Age Books, 1939), Honorable Spy: Exposing Japanese Military Intrigue in the United States (Modern Age Books, 1939), Shrine of the Silver Dollar (Modern Age Books, 1940), Sex, Vice and Business (writing as Monroe Fry) (Ballantine Books, 1959), and his autobiography, A Man In His Time (Horizon Press, 1967).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1922 to 1973, the John L. Spivak Papers comprises correspondence, writings, and memorabilia of the investigative reporter and author (1897-1981).
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-subject files (Boxes 1-12) include Family correspondence (Box 1) containing a few letters, telegrams, and holiday cards from Spivak's wife, daughter and grandson. The remaining files consist primarily of original and photocopied correspondence to and from publishers and those organizations and individuals Spivak contacted regarding his research. Also included are a few subject files with materials from investigative work.
Correspondents include book publishers (Covici Friede, Inc., Harcourt, Brace and Company, Inc., Horizon Press, Inc., Modern Age Books, Inc., Simon & Schuster, Inc.); magazine and newspaper publishers (American Mercury, Easton Publishing Company, Esquire, International News Service, Ken, New Masses, Survey-Survey Graphic); literary, lecture, and Hollywood producers and agents (Ad-Schulberg-Sam Jaffe, Inc., Brandt & Brandt, Charles Hamilton Autographs, Inc., Lester Cohen, Leland Hayward, Inc., Kurt Hellmer, Liebling-Wood, Inc., W. Colston Leigh, Inc., Motion Picture Guild, Inc., and Warner Bros. Pictures/Vitagraph, Inc.); agencies and organizations (American Action, Inc., American Council Against Nazi Propaganda, Inc., American Civil Liberties Union, Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, International Labor Defense); attorneys (Caughlin & Hatten, Foulsten, Siefkin, Foulsten & Morris, Harry Hibschman, Louis Little, Milburn & Semmes, Willard J. Stone, William Stott, Carl Strover); authors and other noted persons (Jules Archer, John Nicholas Beffel, Elizabeth Cousins, Paul Comly French, Frederic J. Haskin, Luther Huston, Oakley C. Johnson, Shaemas O'Sheel, Harry Pollit, George Seldes, Irving Stone, Keith Sward, Mary Heaton Vorse, Kate Warriner, Ella Winter); and federal government departments and politicians. Subject files include Arab fascism, consumer affairs, magazine sales promotion business, Nazi infiltration and propaganda activities, radio and television appearances, and the Scottsboro case.
Correspondence written under one of Spivak's pseudonyms, Monroe Fry, is found in the files of Ballantine Books, Cavalier, Escapade, King Bros. Productions, Inc., Magazine Management Company, Male, Meredith Publishing Company, and Volitant Publishing Corporation. Mercer Plankett (Box 10), an alias Spivak assumed in 1947 while doing research for "Pattern for American Fascism" and "The 'Save the Country' Racket," includes correspondence to and from the U.S. Chamber of Commerce, congressmen, university administrators, and organizations such as American Action, Inc.
There are several folders of correspondence to and from Easton, Pennsylvania area citizens regarding his consumer affairs column, "Action! Express," and includes follow-up correspondence with various businesses and local, state, and federal government offices. Newspaper clippings, memos, press releases, and correspondence with congressional committees and congressmen (Fred B. Rooney, PA) regarding the magazine sales industry investigation comprise the bulk of the column material.
Writings (Boxes 13-34) include notes, drafts, manuscripts, and galley proofs for books, as well as notes, drafts, and clippings of journal and newspaper articles, some of which have handwritten comments. Writings under the name John L. Spivak appear first, followed alphabetically by pseudonym (William Blaise, Howard Booth, Paul Dinsmore, Monroe Fry, Paul Harris, Douglas Horrabin, Al Lippencott, Leslie Lippincott, Sherman L. North, and Shelby Ogden). Materials are then arranged by type (book, journal, newspaper), then publication date. There are also two unpublished manuscripts, Having Fun, reflections of the people and stories Spivak covered throughout his career, and Indictment, an exposéabout the rise of Arab fascism in the U.S. after World War II.
Arranged by type, Memorabilia (Boxes 35-41) includes original and photocopied clippings, arranged by date, of articles about Spivak on such topics as interviewing style, lecture appearances, research, charges made against him by the Georgia prison commissioner, responses to his investigative articles into the conditions in mental institutions, the Whalen forgeries, and Father Coughlin. Book, journal, and lecture publicity materials are arranged by type, then title, and contain clippings, advertisements for books and investigative articles, publishers' catalogs, press releases, and schedules of radio and television appearances. Also arranged by title are book reviews including items published in a variety of newspapers and sent to Spivak via a clipping service. Financial and legal materials, arranged by type, include birth and marriage certificates, contracts with publishers and pay records, litigation documents, travel receipts and passports, and miscellaneous receipts and foreign money. Photographs, arranged by type, include family snapshots, publicity portraits, group photographs, and photographs appearing in Secret Armies. There are also several negatives and test strips of photographs taken while in Central America investigating spy activity. Printed material includes articles from Hebrew newspapers, magazines, announcements, and miscellaneous items. Oversized materials contain issues of magazines, photostats of newspaper articles about Spivak's undercover work in a mental institution, photographs from Georgia Nigger, family portraits taken by Spivak, and book jacket plates and sample book jackets for A Man In His Time.
Subject and Genre Headings
Radicalism; Journalism; Literature -- American Fiction; Spivak, John Louis, 1897-; Authors, American.; Journalists -- United States.; Novelists, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Authors.; Journalists.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John L. Spivak. Additional materials from Zelda Besnoff and Joan I. Covera.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material, See also Memorabilia (Box 34) and Oversized material (Box 40) (Box 1)
- Family correspondence-subject files
  - Klein, Jacqueline, daughter (Box 1)
  - Klein, Peter, grandson (Box 1)
  - Spivak, Mabel, wife (Box 1)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - A, 1 general folder (Box 1)
  - Abzug, Bella (Congress.) (Box 1)
  - "Action! Express", 1968-Sep. 1969; Easton Publishing Company; See also Easton Publishing Company; Magazine Sales Promotion Business; Rooney, Fred B. (Congress.) (Box 1)
  - "Action! Express", Oct. 1969-Jul. 1970 (Box 2)
  - "Action! Express", Aug. 1970-1972; undated (Box 3)
  - "Action! Express", subject files (Box 4)
  - Ad Schulberg-Sam Jaffe, Inc., Hollywood agent (Box 5)
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. (Box 5)
  - Amann, Peter (Box 5)
  - American Action, Inc., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) (Box 5)
  - American Council Against Nazi Propaganda, Inc. (Box 5)
  - American Mercury (Box 5)
  - American Prophetic League, Inc. (Box 5)
  - American Social Hygiene Association (Box 5)
  - American Zionist Council (Box 5)
  - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, See also Forster, Arnold; Goldberg, Miles M. (Box 5)
  - Arab fascism, Documents; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Archer, Jules (Box 6)
  - Ashleigh, Charles (Box 6)
  - Avery, Andrew, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - B, 1 general folder (Box 6)
  - Baer, George (Box 6)
  - Baldwin, Roger N. (Box 6)
  - Ballantine Books, Inc. (Box 6)
  - Barsky, Edward K. (Dr.) (Box 6)
  - Bavley, Benjamin (Box 6)
  - Beffel, John Nicholas (Box 6)
  - Berman Fund, Inc. (Box 6)
  - Better Homes and Gardens, See Meredith Publishing Company
  - Black & White Press (Box 6)
  - Block, Harry (Box 6)
  - Bloor, Ella Reeve "Mother" (Box 6)
  - Bobbs Merrill Company (Box 6)
  - Bone, Homer T. (Congress.) (Box 6)
  - Bouton, S. Miles (Box 6)
  - Bovey, Winifred (Box 6)
  - Bradford, Ralph, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Brandt & Brandt, literary agent; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Braymer, Nan (Box 6)
  - Brodsky, Jack (Box 6)
  - Brooks, Keith L. (Box 6)
  - Browder, Bill (Box 6)
  - Buchman, Beatrice (Box 6)
  - Building Service Employees International Union (Box 6)
  - Butler, Smedley D. (Box 6)
  - C, 1 general folder (Box 6)
  - Canada (Box 6)
  - Canadian Jewish Congress (Box 6)
  - Cardiff, Ira D. (Box 6)
  - Caughlin & Hatten, attorneys (Box 6)
  - Cavalier Magazine, See Fawcett Publications
  - Caxton Printers, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Chagres Camp No. 1 unattached (Box 6)
  - Charles Hamilton Autographs, Inc. (Box 6)
  - Chicago Journal of Commerce, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Christenberry, Robert K., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Christopher Publishing House (Box 6)
  - Clairoun, D. (Box 6)
  - Claude Kendall Publisher (Box 7)
  - Clinton, S. H. M. (Box 7)
  - Cohen, Henry (Rabbi) (Box 7)
  - Cohen, Lester (Box 7)
  - Colburn, John (Box 7)
  - Collier's, See Crowell Publishing Company
  - Committee of Professional Groups for Browder and Ford (Box 7)
  - Communism (Box 7)
  - Communist Party of Canada (Box 7)
  - Communist Party of Massachusetts (Box 7)
  - Comstock, Jim (Box 7)
  - Consumer affairs (Box 7)
  - Coughlin, Charles E. (Rev.) (Box 7)
  - Cousins, Elizabeth (Box 7)
  - Covici Friede, Inc. (Box 7)
  - Cowles, John (Box 7)
  - Crowell Publishing Company (Box 7)
  - Current Controversy (Box 7)
  - D, 1 general folder (Box 7)
  - Daily Worker (Box 7)
  - Dall, Mrs. C. G., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Dalton, James J., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Detroit, MI (City of), See also U.S. Post Office (Detroit) (Box 7)
  - Diamond, Ed (Box 7)
  - Dickstein, Samuel (Congress.) (Box 7)
  - Dillman, David, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Dodd, Martha (Box 7)
  - Dunn, Robert W. (Box 7)
  - E, 1 general folder (Box 7)
  - E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc. (Box 7)
  - Easton Publishing Company, See also "Action! Express" (Easton Publishing Company) (Box 7)
  - Ebenstein, Morris (Box 7)
  - Eby, Cecil D. (Box 7)
  - Emerson, William (Box 7)
  - Escapade Magazine (Box 7)
  - Esquire Magazine, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - European Literary Bureau (Box 7)
  - Exposé Comm. (Box 7)
  - Express, The (Easton, PA), See "Action! Express" (Easton Publishing Company); Easton Publishing Company
  - F, 1 general folder (Box 7)
  - Farrar & Rinehart (Box 7)
  - Fawcett Publications (Box 7)
  - Forster, Arnold, See also Anti Defamation League of B'nai B'rith; Goldberg, Miles M. (Box 7)
  - Foulston, Siefkin, Foulston & Morris (attorneys), See also Sepmeier, Kurt A.; University of Wichita; Wichita Beacon (Box 7)
  - Frankel, Bob (Box 8)
  - French, Paul Comly (Box 8)
  - Friday Magazine (Box 8)
  - Friedman, Bruce J., See Male
  - Fry, Monroe (pseudonym), See Ballantine Books, Inc.; Cavalier Magazine, Escapade Magazine, King Bros. Production Company, Inc., Magazine Management Company, Male, Meredith Publishing Company, Volitant Publishing Corporation
  - Fugl, Harry and Jo (Box 8)
  - G, 1 general folder (Box 8)
  - G.P. Putnam's Sons (Box 8)
  - Ghost Stories Magazine, See Macfadden Publications
  - Gipson, James H., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Goldberg, Miles M., See also Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith; Forster, Arnold; Golden, Harry (Box 8)
  - Golden, Harry (Box 8)
  - H, 1 general folder (Box 8)
  - Harcourt, Brace and Company, Inc. (Box 8)
  - Hart, Merwin K., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Hartz, W. Homer, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Haskin, Frederic J. (Box 8)
  - Hayes, Edward A., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Hearst's International (Box 8)
  - Hellmer, Kurt (Box 8)
  - Henle, James (Box 8)
  - Hibschman, Harry (attorney) (Box 8)
  - Hodges, Betty (Box 8)
  - Hoisington, Harland W. (Box 8)
  - Holiday Magazine (Box 8)
  - Hollywood Anti-Nazi League for the Defense of American Democracy (Box 8)
  - Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc. (Box 8)
  - Horizon Press, Inc., 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Howell, Soskin, & Company, Inc. Publishers (Box 8)
  - Hughes, Langston, See National Committee for the Defense of Political Prisoners
  - Huntington Publishing Company (Box 8)
  - Huston, Luther (Box 8)
  - I, 1 general folder (Box 8)
  - In Fact, Inc. (Box 8)
  - International Labor Defense (Box 8)
  - International News Service (Box 8)
  - J, 1 general folder (Box 8)
  - J.P. Lippincott Company (Box 8)
  - Jackson, Gardner (Box 8)
  - Jewish Examiner (Box 8)
  - Jewish Federation-Council of Greater Los Angeles (Box 8)
  - Jewish Peoples Society (New York) (Box 8)
  - John O'London's Weekly (Box 8)
  - Johnson, Oakley C. (Box 8)
  - Judge, The (Box 8)
  - Justus, J. (Box 8)
  - K, 1 general folder (Box 9)
  - Kahn, Albert E. (Box 9)
  - Kansas (State of) (Box 9)
  - Karr, David (Box 9)
  - Kellyvitch, Fred C. (Box 9)
  - Ken (Box 9)
  - King Bros. Production Company (Box 9)
  - Kisch, Egon Erwin (Box 9)
  - Kopelowna, Bolestawa (Box 9)
  - L, 1 general folder (Box 9)
  - League of American Writers (Box 9)
  - Leland Hayward, Inc. (Hollywood agents) (Box 9)
  - Lenzer, Louis (Box 9)
  - Liberty (Box 9)
  - Liebling-Wood, Inc. (literary agents) (Box 9)
  - Literary Corporation of America (Box 9)
  - Little, Louis (attorney) (Box 9)
  - Little, Brown and Company (Box 9)
  - M, 1 general folder (Box 9)
  - Macfadden Publications (Box 9)
  - Magazine Management Company (Box 9)
  - Magazine Sales Promotion Business, See also "Action! Express" (Easton Publishing Company); Rooney, Fred B. (Congress.) (Box 9)
  - Male (Box 9)
  - Marcantonio, Vito (Congress.), See also Non-Partisan Committee for the Re-Election of Congressman Vito Marcantonio (Box 9)
  - Marcus, Sheldon (Box 9)
  - Mark Twain Journal (Box 9)
  - Marquette University, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Matthews, Francis P., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Mayer, Milton S. (Box 9)
  - McCormick, John W. (Congress.) (Box 9)
  - McDonald, James E., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - McDowell, John (Congress.), See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Menin, Samuel D. (Box 9)
  - Meredith Publishing Company (Box 9)
  - Meyers, Ben (Box 10)
  - Michelson, Herman "Hoy" (Box 10)
  - Michigan (State of) (Box 10)
  - Michie, Allan A. (Box 10)
  - Milburn & Semmes (attorneys) (Box 10)
  - Milstein, Nathan (Box 10)
  - Mineola Police Dept. (NY) (Box 10)
  - Modern Age Books, Inc. (Box 10)
  - Morgan, J. Edward (Box 10)
  - Motion Pictures Guild, Inc. (Box 10)
  - N, 1 general folder (Box 10)
  - Nation, The (Box 10)
  - National Americanism Commission (Box 10)
  - National Broadcasting Company, Inc. (Box 10)
  - National Committee for the Defense of Political Prisoners (Box 10)
  - National Economic Council, Inc., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Nazi infiltration and propaganda activities, 12/29/34; including House of Representatives report on Nazi propaganda activities (Box 10)
  - New Masses (Box 10)
  - New Republic, The (Box 10)
  - New York (City of) (Box 10)
  - New York Mirror (Box 10)
  - New York Post (Box 10)
  - New York Times (Box 10)
  - Newburn, H.K., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Newhouse, Edward (Box 10)
  - News of the World (Box 10)
  - News Research Service, Inc. (Box 10)
  - Nixon, Richard M. (Congress.), See under Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Non-Partisan Committee for the Re-Election of Congressman Vito Marcantonio (Box 10)
  - O, 1 general folder (Box 10)
  - Oglesby, Henry C. (Congress.), See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Old Glory Braves, Inc. (Box 10)
  - O'Sheel, Shaemas (Box 10)
  - P, 1 general folder (Box 10)
  - PACE-NY (Box 10)
  - Paley, Emily (Box 10)
  - Pallet, Earl M., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Panama American, The (Box 10)
  - Partido Comunista de Mexico (Box 10)
  - Patterson, Eugene (Box 10)
  - Pennsylvania (Commonwealth of) (Box 10)
  - Peterson, J. Hardin (Congress.), See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Pettit, Walter J. (Box 10)
  - Philadelphia Inquirer (Box 10)
  - Philadelphia Workers School (Box 10)
  - Pickens, William (Box 10)
  - Plain Talk Magazine (Box 10)
  - Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias) (Box 10)
  - Pollitt, Harry (Box 10)
  - Popham, John (Box 10)
  - Pottsville Republican (Box 10)
  - Pozner, Vladmir (Box 10)
  - Prevention (Box 10)
  - Prince, Frank J. (Box 10)
  - R, 1 general folder (Box 11)
  - Rachlis, Jack (Box 11)
  - Radio and television appearances, See also specific radio and television stations (Box 11)
  - Ragan, Sam (Box 11)
  - Reader's Digest, The (Box 11)
  - Robert S. Abbott Publishing Company (Box 11)
  - Rooney, Fred B. (Congress.), See also "Action! Express" (Easton Publishing Company); Magazine Sales Promotion Business (Box 11)
  - Roos, Joseph (Box 11)
  - Rose, Fred (Box 11)
  - Roth, Lester WM (Box 11)
  - Rothman, Walter (Box 11)
  - Rudy, Charles and Lorraine (Box 11)
  - S, 1 general folder (Box 11)
  - Sacco-Vanzetti Commemoration Committee (Box 11)
  - Sacramento Union (Box 11)
  - Schmidt, Emerson P., See under Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Scott, Byron N. (Congress.) (Box 11)
  - Scottsboro Trial (Scottsboro, AL) (Box 11)
  - Schwimmer, Rosika (Box 11)
  - Seattle New World (Box 11)
  - Securities Acceptance Corp., See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Seldes, George (Box 11)
  - Sepmeier, Kurt A., See also Foulston, Siefkin, Foulston & Morris (attorneys); University of Wichita; Wichita Beacon (Box 11)
  - Stanley, James A. (Congress.) (Box 11)
  - Simon and Schuster, Inc. (Box 11)
  - Sklar & Peters, Inc. (playwrights) (Box 11)
  - Solomon, Anna (Box 11)
  - Soule, Frederick R. (Box 11)
  - Soviet Union Review (Box 11)
  - Stackpole Sons, Publishers (Box 11)
  - Stag, See Magazine Management Company
  - Steffens, Peter (Box 11)
  - Stephens, Louise (Box 11)
  - Stone, Irving and Jean (Box 11)
  - Stone, Willard J. (Box 11)
  - Story and the Story Press (Box 11)
  - Stott, William (Box 11)
  - Strover, Carl (Box 11)
  - Strunsky, Michael and Jean (Box 11)
  - Strunsky, W. English and Lucy (Box 11)
  - Survey-Survey Graphic (Box 11)
  - Sward, Keith (Box 11)
  - T, 1 general folder (Box 11)
  - Thomas, J. Parnell (Congress.), See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Toronto Star (Box 11)
  - Towle, Marion (Box 11)
  - Tuckahoe Record (Box 11)
  - U, 1 general folder (Box 11)
  - University of Wichita, See also Foulston, Siefkin, Foulston & Morris (attorneys); Sepmeier, Kurt A.; Wichita Beacon (Box 11)
  - University of Minnesota, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - University of Oregon, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - University of Wisconsin, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - U.S. Chamber of Commerce, See also Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias) (Box 11)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission (Box 11)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture, See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - U.S. Department of State (Box 11)
  - U.S. Department of the Navy (Box 11)
  - U.S. Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 11)
  - U.S. Federal Works Agency (Box 11)
  - U.S. Internal Revenue Service (Box 11)
  - U.S. National Aeronautics and Space Administration (Box 11)
  - U.S. Office of Alien Property Custodian (Box 11)
  - U.S. Office of Price Administration (Box 11)
  - U.S. Post Office (Detroit) (Box 11)
  - U.S. Treasury Department (Box 11)
  - U.S. War Department (Box 11)
  - U.S. Works Progress Administration (Box 11)
  - V, 1 general folder (Box 12)
  - Vail, Richard B. (Congress.), See Plankett, Mercer (Spivak alias)
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars (Box 12)
  - Victor Gollanz, Ltd. (Box 12)
  - Vitagraph, Inc. (Warner Bros.) (Box 12)
  - Volitant Publishing Corporation (Box 12)
  - Von Platen Luder, Hugo (Box 12)
  - Vorse, Heaton White (Box 12)
  - Vorse, Mary Heaton (Box 12)
  - W, 1 general folder (Box 12)
  - WBAI (New York) (Box 12)
  - WBKB-TV (Chicago) (Box 12)
  - WIBF-TV (Philadelphia) (Box 12)
  - WMAL-TV (Washington, D.C.) (Box 12)